<?xml version='1.0' encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="desktop">

	<title>Testing Dektop applications</title>
	<para>
		Demoiselle Behave Framework has a specific Runner for
		Desktop application (Swing) tests. This chapter talks about this
		subject. It should be noted that from version 1.6.0 the
		Demoiselle Behave starts using the AssertJ framework in
		substitution of Fest, which had the project discontinued in the
		community. The Fest runner is in the process of discontinuing
		and, in existing projects, it is recommended the replacement of
		it by the AssertJ runner.
	</para>
	<section>
		<title>Starting a project using Archetype (Project Model)
		</title>
		<para>
			When you create a project it is possible to select archetype
			<emphasis>jbehave-assertj-archetype</emphasis>
			for having a fast beginning of a Desktop (Swing)
			test automation project.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Starting a project using an existing project (Project
			WebDriver)</title>
		<para>
			For changing an existing project into a functional Desktop test project
			it is enough to change runner and change appropriated
			settings.

			Change runner dependency.

			<programlisting>
				<![CDATA[<dependency>
				<groupId>br.gov.frameworkdemoiselle.component.behave</groupId>
				<artifactId>demoiselle-behave-runner-assertj</artifactId>
				<version>1.x.x</version>
				<scope>test</scope>
				</dependency>]]>
			</programlisting>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Desktop Configurations</title>
		<para>
			All already quoted settings that are related to
			Desktop can be used too. Below are specific
			settings for Desktop:

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					Add project into
					<emphasis>classpath</emphasis>
					of tests project;
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					Add setting
					<emphasis>behave.runner.app.mainClass</emphasis>
					into properties with name of class that starts Desktop
					project.
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Mappings</title>
		<para>
			Desktop runner uses 3 types of locators, according list below:
						
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<citetitle>Label:</citetitle> Select screen object that has visible text;
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<citetitle>Name:</citetitle> Select screen object that has user selected identifier;
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<citetitle>ClassName:</citetitle> Select screen object that has defined class (JPanel, JButton...).  
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			Additionally to these locators it is possible to select the index that object is using, such as annotation @ElementIndex, in following sample:
			
			<programlisting>@ElementMap(name = "Nome do Elemento na História", locatorType = ElementLocatorType.ClassName, locator = "JTextField")
<citetitle>@ElementIndex(index = 1)</citetitle>
private TextField atributo;</programlisting>

			By default object index is 0 (Zero).
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
